I'd like to take you to another world.
أود أن آخذكم إلى عالم آخر
And I'd like to share
وأود أن أشارككم
a 45 year-old love story
قصة حب دامت 45 سنة
with the poor,
مع الفقراء
living on less than one dollar a day.
الذين يعيشون على أقل من دولار يومياً
I went to a very elitist, snobbish,
لقد تلقيت تعليم نخبوي ومتعالِ
expensive education in India,
ومكلف في الهند
and that almost destroyed me.
وهذا كاد أن يحطمني
I was all set
كنت مستعداً
to be a diplomat, teacher, doctor --
لأن أصبح دبلوماسياً أو معلماً أو طبيباً
all laid out.
كلها كانت متاحة أمامي
Then, I don't look it, but I was the Indian national squash champion
بعد ذلك أصبحت بطل السكواتش الوطني في الهند، ولو أني لا أبدو كذلك
for three years.
على مدى ثلاث سنوات
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
The whole world was laid out for me.
كان العالم كله في قبضة يدي
Everything was at my feet.
كل شيء كان تحت قدمي
I could do nothing wrong.
لم أكن لأخطيء أبداً
And then I thought out of curiosity
وفكرت بدافع الفضول
I'd like to go and live and work
بأنني أريد أن أذهب وأعيش وأعمل
and just see what a village is like.
وأن أرى فقط كيف تكون القرية
So in 1965,
ولذلك في عام 1965
I went to what was called the worst Bihar famine in India,
ذهبت إلى ما كان يسمى أسوأ مجاعة في ولاية بيهار بالهند
and I saw starvation, death,
ورأيت الجوع والموت
people dying of hunger, for the first time.
لأول مرة في حياتي أرى الناس تموت من الجوع
It changed my life.
غيرت حياتي
I came back home,
فعدت إلى الديار
told my mother,
وقلت لوالدتي
"I'd like to live and work in a village."
"أريد أن أعيش وأعمل في قرية"
Mother went into a coma.
دخلت أمي في غيبوبة
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
"What is this?
"ما هذا؟
The whole world is laid out for you, the best jobs are laid out for you,
العالم بأسره بين يديك وتستطيع الحصول على أفضل الوظائف
and you want to go and work in a village?
وتريد أن تذهب لتعمل في قرية؟
I mean, is there something wrong with you?"
أقصد، هل تعاني من خطب ما؟"
I said, "No, I've got the best eduction.
فقلت: "لا، حصلت على أفضل تعليم
It made me think.
وذلك جعلني أفكر
And I wanted to give something back
وأردت أن أعطي شيئاً بالمقابل
in my own way."
بطريقتي الخاصة"
"What do you want to do in a village?
"ماذا تريد أن تفعل في قرية؟
No job, no money,
لا عمل ولا نقود
no security, no prospect."
ولا أمان ولا إمكانيات"
I said, "I want to live
فقلت: "أريد أن أعيش
and dig wells for five years."
وأحفر الآبار على مدى خمس سنوات"
"Dig wells for five years?
"تحفر الآبار لمدة خمس سنوات؟
You went to the most expensive school and college in India,
إرتدت أغلى المدارس والجامعات في الهند
and you want to dig wells for five years?"
وتريد أن تحفر الآبار لمدة خمس سنوات؟"
She didn't speak to me for a very long time,
ولم تكلمني لوقت طويل جداً
because she thought I'd let my family down.
لأنها أعتقدت بأني سأخيب آمال عائلتي
But then,
ولكن حينها
I was exposed to the most extraordinary knowledge and skills
تعرضت للمعرفة والمهارات الأكثر إستثنائية
that very poor people have,
والتي يمتلكها الناس الفقراء جداً
which are never brought into the mainstream --
والتي لم تجلب أبداً لوسط التيار
which is never identified, respected,
والتي لم يتعرف عليها ولم تحترم
applied on a large scale.
ولم تطبق على مستوى كبير
And I thought I'd start a Barefoot College --
وفكرت بأن أبدأ كلية بيرفوت
college only for the poor.
كلية للفقراء فقط
What the poor thought was important
ما كان يعتقد الفقراء بأنه مهم
would be reflected in the college.
سينعكس في الكلية
I went to this village for the first time.
ذهبت إلى هذه القرية للمرة الأولى
Elders came to me
وجاء الشيوخ إليّ
and said, "Are you running from the police?"
وقالوا: "هل أنت هارب من الشرطة؟"
I said, "No."
فقلت: "لا"
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
"You failed in your exam?"
"هل فشلت في اختبارك؟"
I said, "No."
فقلت: "لا"
"You didn't get a government job?" I said, "No."
"لم تحصل على وظيفة حكومية؟" فقلت: "لا"
"What are you doing here?
"ماذا تفعل هنا؟
Why are you here?
لماذا أنت هنا؟
The education system in India
النظام التعليمي في الهند
makes you look at Paris and New Delhi and Zurich;
يجعلك تنظر إلى باريس ونيوديلهي وزيورخ
what are you doing in this village?
ما الذي تفعله في هذه القرية؟
Is there something wrong with you you're not telling us?"
هل هناك خطب ما بك ولا تريد إخبارنا به؟"
I said, "No, I want to actually start a college
فقلت: "لا أنا حقا أريد إنشاء كلية
only for the poor.
للفقراء فقط
What the poor thought was important would be reflected in the college."
وما يعتقد الفقراء بأنه مهم سينعكس في هذه الكلية"
So the elders gave me some very sound and profound advice.
فنصحني الشيوخ نصيحة سليمة وعميقة جداً
They said, "Please,
فقالوا: "رجاءاً،
don't bring anyone with a degree and qualification
لا تجلب أي شخص يمتلك شهادة ومؤهلات
into your college."
إلى كليتك"
So it's the only college in India
ولذلك هي الكلية الوحيدة في الهند
where, if you should have a Ph.D. or a Master's,
حيث إذا كنت تمتلك شهادة الدكتوراه أو الماجستير
you are disqualified to come.
فأنت غير مؤهل للعمل بها
You have to be a cop-out or a wash-out or a dropout
يجب أن تكون غير مسئول أو فاشل أو تارك للدراسة
to come to our college.
لتأتي لكليتنا
You have to work with your hands.
يجب عليك العمل بيديك
You have to have a dignity of labor.
يجب أن تمتلك كرامة العمل
You have to show that you have a skill that you can offer to the community
يجب عليك إثبات أن لديك مهارة تستطيع تقديمها للمجتمع
and provide a service to the community.
وتقدم خدمة للمجتمع
So we started the Barefoot College,
وبدأنا كلية بيرفوت
and we redefined professionalism.
وأعدنا تعريف الإحتراف
Who is a professional?
من هو المحترف؟
A professional is someone
المحترف هو الشخص
who has a combination of competence,
الذي يمتلك مجموعة من الكفاءات
confidence and belief.
والثقة والإيمان
A water diviner is a professional.
عراف المياه هو محترف
A traditional midwife
القابلة التقليدية
is a professional.
محترفة
A traditional bone setter is a professional.
واضع الوعاء التقليدي محترف
These are professionals all over the world.
هؤلاء محترفون في كل بقاع العالم
You find them in any inaccessible village around the world.
فتراهم في أي قرية نائية حول العالم
And we thought that these people should come into the mainstream
ورأينا بأن هؤلاء الناس يجب أن يوضعوا في صلب التيار
and show that the knowledge and skills that they have
ونبين بأن المعرفة والمهارات التي يمتلكونها
is universal.
عالمية
It needs to be used, needs to be applied,
يجب أن تستخدم ويجب أن تطبق
needs to be shown to the world outside --
يجب أن تعرض للعالم الخارجي
that these knowledge and skills
بأن هذه المعرفة والمهارات
are relevant even today.
وثيقة الصلة حتى اليوم
So the college works
وبذلك تعمل الكلية
following the lifestyle and workstyle of Mahatma Gandhi.
مقتدية بنمط حياة وأسلوب عمل المهاتما غاندي
You eat on the floor, you sleep on the floor, you work on the floor.
تأكل على الأرض وتنام على الأرض وتعمل على الأرض
There are no contracts, no written contracts.
لا يوجد عقود، لا يوجد عقود مكتوبة
You can stay with me for 20 years, go tomorrow.
يمكنك البقاء معي لمدة 20 سنة والذهاب غداً
And no one can get more than $100 a month.
ولا يمكن لأحد أن يحصل على أكثر من 100$ شهرياً
You come for the money, you don't come to Barefoot College.
إذا كنت تبحث عن المال فلا تأتي لكلية بيرفوت
You come for the work and the challenge,
وإذا كنت تبحث عن العمل والتحدي
you'll come to the Barefoot College.
فستأتي إلى كلية بيرفوت
That is where we want you to try crazy ideas.
فهناك نريدك أن تحاول وتصنع الأفكار
Whatever idea you have, come and try it.
فأياً كانت الفكرة فتعال وجربها
It doesn't matter if you fail.
لا يهم إن أخفقت
Battered, bruised, you start again.
أو تلقيت ضربات أو كدمات عليك أن تبدأ من جديد
It's the only college where the teacher is the learner
إنها الكلية الوحيدة حيث يكون المعلم هو المتعلم
and the learner is the teacher.
ويكون المتعلم هو المعلم
And it's the only college where we don't give a certificate.
وهي الكلية الوحيدة حيث لا نعطي شهادات
You are certified by the community you serve.
فإنه مشهود لك من خلال المجتمع الذي تخدمه
You don't need a paper to hang on the wall
فإنك لا تحتاج لورقة تعلقها على الحائط
to show that you are an engineer.
لتثبت بأنك مهندس
So when I said that,
ولذلك عندما قلت هذا
they said, "Well show us what is possible. What are you doing?
قالوا: "أرنا ما هو الممكن. ماذا تفعل؟
This is all mumbo-jumbo if you can't show it on the ground."
هذا كله هراء إذا لم تستطع إثباته على أرض الواقع"
So we built the first Barefoot College
ولذلك بنينا أول كلية بيرفوت
in 1986.
في 1986
It was built by 12 Barefoot architects
بنيت من قبل 12 مهندس بيرفوت معماري
who can't read and write,
والذين لا يستطيعون القراءة ولا الكتابة
built on $1.50 a sq. ft.
بنيت على 1.5$ للقدم المربع
150 people lived there, worked there.
عاش وعمل 150 فرد هناك
They got the Aga Khan Award for Architecture in 2002.
وحصوا على جائزة الآغا خان للعمارة في عام 2002
But then they suspected, they thought there was an architect behind it.
ولكنهم قاموا بالشك بعدها، إعتقدوا بأن وراءها مهندس معماري
I said, "Yes, they made the blueprints,
فقلت: "نعم، قاموا برسم المخططات
but the Barefoot architects actually constructed the college."
ولكن معماريو بيرفوت بنوا الكلية"
We are the only ones who actually returned the award for $50,000,
وكنا نحن الوحيدين الذين أعادوا الجائزة التي تبلغ 50،000$
because they didn't believe us,
لأنهم لم يصدقونا
and we thought that they were actually casting aspersions
وكنا نظن أنهم كانوا يطعنون
on the Barefoot architects of Tilonia.
في مهندسين بيرفوت في تايلونيا
I asked a forester --
سألت بستاني --
high-powered, paper-qualified expert --
خبير ذو نفوذ عالية ومؤهل ورقي
I said, "What can you build in this place?"
فقلت: "ما الذي يمكنك بناءه في هذا المكان؟"
He had one look at the soil and said, "Forget it. No way.
فألقى نظرة واحدة على التربة وقالك "أنسى الموضوع. لا جدوى
Not even worth it.
إنه حتى لا يستحق التعب
No water, rocky soil."
لا يوجد ماء والتربة متحجرة"
I was in a bit of a spot.
كنت في موقف حرج قليلاً
And I said, "Okay, I'll go to the old man in village
وقلت: "حسناً سأذهب إلى الرجل الكبير في القرية
and say, 'What should I grow in this spot?'"
وأقول: ما الذي يجب أن أزرعه في هذه البقعة؟"
He looked quietly at me and said,
فنظر إليّ بهدوء وقال
"You build this, you build this, you put this, and it'll work."
"تبني هذا وتبني هذا وتضع هذا وسيعمل"
This is what it looks like today.
وهذا شكلها اليوم
Went to the roof,
ذهبت إلى السطح
and all the women said, "Clear out.
وجميع النساء قالوا: "أخرج
The men should clear out because we don't want to share this technology with the men.
يجب على جميع الرجال الخروج لأننا لا نريد مشاركة هذه التقنية مع الرجال
This is waterproofing the roof."
هذا يمنع تسريب المياه من السطح"
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
It is a bit of jaggery, a bit of urens
إنه قليل من السكر الأسمر وقليل من الأورين
and a bit of other things I don't know.
وقليل من أشياء أخرى لا أعرفها
But it actually doesn't leak.
ولكنها لا تتسرب فعلاً
Since 1986, it hasn't leaked.
لم تتسرب المياه منذ 1986
This technology, the women will not share with the men.
هذه التقنية التي لن تشاركها النساء مع الرجال
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
It's the only college
إنها الكلية الوحيدة
which is fully solar-electrified.
التي تعمل كهرباءها على الطاقة الشمسية بالكامل
All the power comes from the sun.
كل الطاقة تأتي من الشمس
45 kilowatts of panels on the roof.
لوحات ذات 45 كيلو واط فوق السطح
And everything works off the sun for the next 25 years.
ويعمل كل شيء قبالة الشمس لمدة الـ 25 سنة القادمة
So long as the sun shines,
طالما أن الشمس تشرق
we'll have no problem with power.
فإنه لن يكون لدينا مشكلة من الطاقة
But the beauty is
ولكن الجمال هو
that is was installed
أنها طبقت
by a priest, a Hindu priest,
من قبل كاهن، كاهن هندوسي
who's only done eight years of primary schooling --
والذي قام بدارسة ثمان سنوات فقط من المرحلة الإبتدائية
never been to school, never been to college.
لم يذهب للمدرسة قط ولم يذهب للكلية أبداً
He knows more about solar
ولكنه يعرف عن الطاقة الشمسية أكثر
than anyone I know anywhere in the world guaranteed.
من أي أحد في أي مكان في العالم وأنا أضمن ذلك
Food, if you come to the Barefoot College,
الطعام، حينما تأتي لكلية بيرفوت
is solar cooked.
مطبوخ بالطاقة الشمسية
But the people who fabricated that solar cooker
ولكن هؤلاء الناس الذين صنعوا الموقد العامل بالطاقة الشمسية
are women,
هن نساء
illiterate women,
نساء أميات
who actually fabricate
والذين يصنعون بالفعل
the most sophisticated solar cooker.
موقد الطاقة الشمسية الأكثر تطوراً
It's a parabolic Scheffler solar cooker.
إنه موقد طاقة شمسية مكافئ ولا يحتاج إلى طاه
Unfortunately, they're almost half German,
لسوء الحظ، أنهم تقريباً نصف ألمانيات
they're so precise.
أنهن دقيقات جداً
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
You'll never find Indian women so precise.
لن تجد أبداً إمرأة هندية دقيقة جداً
Absolutely to the last inch,
لآخر شبر تماماً
they can make that cooker.
يستطعن صنع هذه الطنجرة
And we have 60 meals twice a day
ونحن نطبخ 60 وجبة مرتين يومياً
of solar cooking.
من الطبخ بالطاقة الشمسية
We have a dentist --
لدينا طبيبة أسنان
she's a grandmother, illiterate, who's a dentist.
إنها جدة أمية وهي طبيبة أسنان
She actually looks after the teeth
إنها تهتم بأسنان
of 7,000 children.
7000 طفل
Barefoot technology:
تكنولوجيا بيرفوت:
this was 1986 -- no engineer, no architect thought of it --
كانت هذه سنة 1986 -- لم يفكر بها لا مهندسين ولا معماريين --
but we are collecting rainwater from the roofs.
ولكننا نقوم بجمع مياه الأمطار من السطوح
Very little water is wasted.
يتم إهدار ماء قليل
All the roofs are connected underground
جميع الأسقف موصولة تحت الأرض
to a 400,000 liter tank,
بخزان ذو سعة 400،000 لتر
and no water is wasted.
ولا يتم إهدار أي قطرة ماء
If we have four years of drought, we still have water on the campus,
لو صادفنا أربعة سنوات من الجفاف سيظل الماء متوفر عندنا في الحرم
because we collect rainwater.
لأننا نجمع ماء المطر
60 percent of children don't go to school,
60 بالمئة من الأطفال لا يرتادون المدرسة
because they have to look after animals --
لأنه يجب عليهم رعاية الحيوانات
sheep, goats --
الخرفان والماعز
domestic chores.
والأعمال المنزلية
So we thought of starting a school
ولذلك فكرنا بإنشاء مدرسة
at night for the children.
في المساء للأطفال
Because the night schools of Tilonia,
وذلك لأن المدارس الليلية لتايلونيا
over 75,000 children have gone through these night schools.
أكثر من 75،000 طفل إرتاد هذه المدارس الليلية
Because it's for the convenience of the child;
لأنها لراحة الطفل
it's not for the convenience of the teacher.
إنها ليست لراحة المعلم
And what do we teach in these schools?
وماذا نعلم في هذه المدارس؟
Democracy, citizenship,
الديمقراطية والوطنية
how you should measure your land,
كيف يمكنك قياس أرضك
what you should do if you're arrested,
ما الذي يجب عليك فعله لو قبض عليك
what you should do if your animal is sick.
ما الذي يجب عليك فعله إذا مرض أحد حيواناتك
This is what we teach in the night schools.
هذا ما نقوم بتعليمه في المدارس الليلية
But all the schools are solar-lit.
ولكن جميع المدارس مضاءة بإستخدام الطاقة الشمسية
Every five years
كل خمس سنوات
we have an election.
نعمل إنتخابات
Between six to 14 year-old children
بين أطفال مابين الـ 6 إلى 14 سنة
participate in a democratic process,
يشتركون في عملية ديمقراطية
and they elect a prime minister.
وينتخبون رئيس وزراء
The prime minister is 12 years old.
رئيسة الوزراء تبلغ من العمر 12 سنة
She looks after 20 goats in the morning,
وترعى 20 معزة في الصباح
but she's prime minister in the evening.
ولكنها رئيسة وزراء في المساء
She has a cabinet,
لديها مجلس وزراء
a minister of education, a minister for energy, a minister for health.
وزير تعليم ووزير طاقة ووزير صحة
And they actually monitor and supervise
وإنهم يرصدون بالفعل ويشرفون
150 schools for 7,000 children.
على 150 مدرسة لـ 7،000 طفل
She got the World's Children's Prize five years ago,
حصلت على جائزة الطفل العالمية قبل خمس سنوات
and she went to Sweden.
وذهبت إلى السويد
First time ever going out of her village.
لأول مرة تخرج فيها من قريتها على الإطلاق
Never seen Sweden.
لم ترى السويد قط
Wasn't dazzled at all by what was happening.
ولكنها لم تبهر أبداً بما كان يحدث
And the Queen of Sweden, who's there,
وملكة السويد التي كانت هناك
turned to me and said, "Can you ask this child where she got her confidence from?
إلتفتت إليّ وقالتك "هل يمكنك أن تسأل هذه الطفلة من أين حصلت على ثقتها؟
She's only 12 years old,
فإنها في عمر الثانية عشر فقط
and she's not dazzled by anything."
وهي لم تبهر بأي شيء"
And the girl, who's on her left,
وقامت الفتاة الواقفة إلى يسارها
turned to me and looked at the queen straight in the eye
بالإلتفات إليّ ونظرت إلى عينيّ الملكة مباشرة
and said, "Please tell her I'm the prime minister."
وقالت: "أرجوك أخبرها بأنني أنا وزيرة الخارجية"
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Where the percentage of illiteracy is very high,
حيث تكون نسبة الأمية عالية جداً
we use puppetry.
نستخدم العرائس
Puppets is the way we communicate.
الدمى هي الطريقة التي نتواصل بها
You have Jokhim Chacha
لديك يواقيم تشاتشا
who is 300 years old.
والذي يبلغ من العمر 300 عام
He is my psychoanalyst. He is my teacher.
هو محللي النفسي وهو معلمي
He's my doctor. He's my lawyer.
وهو أيضاً طبيبي ومحاميي
He's my donor.
ومتبرعي كذلك
He actually raises money,
هو بالفعل يجمع المال
solves my disputes.
ويحل نزاعاتي
He solves my problems in the village.
ويحل مشاكل في القرية
If there's tension in the village,
إذا كان هناك توتر في القرية
if attendance at the schools goes down
لو إنخفض معدل الحضور في المدرسة
and there's a friction between the teacher and the parent,
ولو كان هناك خلاف بين المعلم والأهل
the puppet calls the teacher and the parent in front of the whole village
تستدعي الدمية المعلم والوالد أمام القرية بأكملها
and says, "Shake hands.
ويقول: "تصافحوا
The attendance must not drop."
الحضور يجب أن لا ينخفض"
These puppets
هذه الدمى
are made out of recycled World Bank reports.
مصنوعة من تقارير البنك الدولي المعاد تدويرها
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
So this decentralized, demystified approach
هذا النهج الواضح والبسيط
of solar-electrifying villages,
من كهربة القرى بالطاقة الشمسية
we've covered all over India
والذي قمنا من خلاله بتغطية جميع قرى الهند
from Ladakh up to Bhutan --
من اداخ حتى بوتان --
all solar-electrified villages
جميعها تعمل على الطاقة الشمسية
by people who have been trained.
من قبل أناس دربوا
And we went to Ladakh,
وذهبنا إلى اداخ
and we asked this woman --
وسألنا هذه المرأة --
this, at minus 40, you have to come out of the roof,
بأن تنزل من السطح، هذا وكانت درجة الحرارة 40 تحت الصفر
because there's no place, it was all snowed up on both sides --
لأنه لم يكن هناك مكان كان كل شيء مغطى بالثلج حتى على الجانبين
and we asked this woman,
وسألنا هذه المرأة:
"What was the benefit you had
"ما الفائدة التي جنيتها
from solar electricity?"
من كهرباء الطاقة الشمسية؟"
And she thought for a minute and said,
وفكرت لدقيقة واحدة وقالت:
"It's the first time I can see my husband's face in winter."
"إنها المرة الأولى التي أستطعت بها رؤية وجه زوجي في الشتاء"
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Went to Afghanistan.
ذهبنا إلى أفغانستان
One lesson we learned in India
درس واحد تعلمناه في الهند
was men are untrainable.
هو أن الرجال لا يمكن تدريبهم
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Men are restless,
فالرجال لا يرتاحون
men are ambitious,
والرجال طموحين
men are compulsively mobile,
والرجال متنقلون بشكل إلزامي
and they all want a certificate.
وجميعهم يريدون شهادة
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
All across the globe, you have this tendency
وتجدون هذا الميل في جميع أنحاء العالم
of men wanting a certificate.
لرجال يريدون شهادة
Why? Because they want to leave the village
لماذا؟ لأنهم يريدون ترك القرية
and go to a city, looking for a job.
والذهاب إلى مدينة ليبحثوا عن عمل
So we came up with a great solution:
ولذلك جئنا بحل عظيم
train grandmothers.
وهو تدريب الجدات
What's the best way of communicating
ما هي أفضل طريقة للتواصل
in the world today?
في العالم اليوم؟
Television? No.
التلفاز؟ لا
Telegraph? No.
الرسائل؟ لا
Telephone? No.
الهاتف؟ لا
Tell a woman.
أخبر إمرأة
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
So we went to Afghanistan for the first time,
فذهبنا إلى أفغانستان للمرة الأولى
and we picked three women
وأخترنا ثلاث نساء
and said, "We want to take them to India."
وقلنا: "نريد أخذهم إلى الهند"
They said, "Impossible. They don't even go out of their rooms,
وقالوا: "مستحيل. فإنهم لا يتركون غرفهم حتى
and you want to take them to India."
وانتم تريدون أخذهم إلى الهند"
I said, "I'll make a concession. I'll take the husbands along as well."
فقلت: "سأقدم تنازل. سآخذ الأزواج كذلك"
So I took the husbands along.
وقمت بأخذ أزواجهم أيضاً
Of course, the women were much more intelligent than the men.
بالطبع، كن النساء أكثر ذكاء من الرجال
In six months,
خلال ستة أشهر
how do we train these women?
كيف نغير هؤلاء النساء؟
Sign language.
لغة الإشارة
You don't choose the written word.
فإنك لا تختار الكلمة المكتوبة
You don't choose the spoken word.
ولا تختار الكلمة المنطوقة
You use sign language.
بل تستخدم لغة الإشارة
And in six months
وفي ستة أشهر
they can become solar engineers.
يمكنهن أن يصبحن مهندسات طاقة شمسية
They go back and solar-electrify their own village.
يعدن إلى قراهن ويكهربن قراهن بالطاقة الشمسية
This woman went back
عادت هذه المرأة
and solar-electrified the first village,
وقامت بكهربة هذه القرية بالطاقة الشمسية
set up a workshop --
أعدت ورشة عمل
the first village ever to be solar-electrified in Afghanistan
أول قرية يتم كهربتها بالطاقة الشمسية في أفغانستان
[was] by the three women.
كانت من قبل ثلاث نساء
This woman
هذه المرأة
is an extraordinary grandmother.
هي جدة استثنائية
55 years old, and she's solar-electrified 200 houses for me in Afghanistan.
تبلغ من العمر 55 سنة وقامت بكهربة 200 بيت لي في أفغانستان
And they haven't collapsed.
ولم ينهاروا
She actually went and spoke to an engineering department in Afghanistan
ذهبت بالفعل وتحدثت إلى قسم هندسة في أفغانستان
and told the head of the department
وقالت لرئيسه
the difference between AC and DC.
الفرق بين التيار المتردد والتيار المستمر
He didn't know.
هو لم يكن يعلم
Those three women have trained 27 more women
قمن هؤلاء النساء الثلاث بتدريب 27 إمرأة أخرى
and solar-electrified 100 villages in Afghanistan.
وكهربن 100 قرية بالطاقة الشمسية في أفغانستان
We went to Africa,
ذهبنا إلى أفريقيا
and we did the same thing.
وفعلنا الشيء ذاته
All these women sitting at one table from eight, nine countries,
كل هؤلاء النساء من ثمان أو تسع دول مختلفة مجتمعات على طاولة واحدة
all chatting to each other, not understanding a word,
جميعهن يتكلمن مع بعضهن البعض ولا أحد يفهم الآخر
because they're all speaking a different language.
لأنهن يتحدثن لغات مختلفة
But their body language is great.
ولكن لغة اجسادهن ممتازة
They're speaking to each other
إنهم يتحدثن سوياً
and actually becoming solar engineers.
وبالفعل أصبحن مهندسات طاقة شمسية
I went to Sierra Leone,
ذهبت إلى سيراليون
and there was this minister driving down in the dead of night --
وكان هناك وزير يقود السيارة في جوف الليل
comes across this village.
يعبر من قرب هذه القرية
Comes back, goes into the village, says, "Well what's the story?"
ويعود ويدخل القرية ويقول: "حسناً، ما القصة؟"
They said, "These two grandmothers ... "
فقالوا: "هاتان الجدتان..."
"Grandmothers?" The minister couldn't believe what was happening.
"جدات؟" لم يصدق الوزير الذي يحدث
"Where did they go?" "Went to India and back."
"أين ذهبتا؟" "ذهبتا للهند وعادتا"
Went straight to the president.
ذهب مباشرة إلى الرئيس
He said, "Do you know there's a solar-electrified village in Sierra Leone?"
وقال: "هل تعلم أن هناك قرية مكهربة بالطاقة الشمسية في سيراليون؟"
He said, "No." Half the cabinet went to see the grandmothers the next day.
فأجاب: "لا" ذهب نصف مجلس الوزراء ليرى الجدتان في اليوم التالي
"What's the story."
"ما القصة؟"
So he summoned me and said, "Can you train me 150 grandmothers?"
فا إستدعاني وقال: "هل تستطيع تدريب 150 جدة لي؟"
I said, "I can't, Mr. President.
فقلت: "لا أستطيع ياسيدي الرئيس
But they will. The grandmothers will."
لكن هن سيفعلن. الجدتان سيفعلن"
So he built me the first Barefoot training center in Sierra Leone.
فبنى لي أول مركز بيرفوت للتدريب في سيراليون
And 150 grandmothers have been trained in Sierra Leone.
وتم تدريب 150 جدة في سيراليون
Gambia:
غامبيا:
we went to select a grandmother in Gambia.
ذهبنا لنختار جدة في غامبيا
Went to this village.
ذهبنا إلى هذه القرية
I knew which woman I would like to take.
كنت أعرف أي جدة أريد أن آخذ
The community got together and said, "Take these two women."
إجتمع المجتمع وقال: "خذ هاتين المرأتين"
I said, "No, I want to take this woman."
فقلت: "لا، أريد أن آخذ هذه المرأة"
They said, "Why? She doesn't know the language. You don't know her."
قالوا: "لماذا؟ إنها لا تعرف اللغة. أنت لا تعرفها"
I said, "I like the body language. I like the way she speaks."
فقلت: "أحب لغة الجسد. تعجبني الطريقة التي تتحدث بها"
"Difficult husband; not possible."
"زوجها صعب: مستحيل"
Called the husband, the husband came,
استدعيت الزوج وأتى
swaggering, politician, mobile in his hand. "Not possible."
مختال وسياسي وحاملاً هاتفاً نقالاً بيده "مستحيل"
"Why not?" "The woman, look how beautiful she is."
"لماذا؟" "أنظر كم هذه المرأة جميلة"
I said, "Yeah, she is very beautiful."
فقلت: "نعم إنها جميلة جداً"
"What happens if she runs off with an Indian man?"
"ماذا سيحدث لو هربت مع رجل هندي؟"
That was his biggest fear.
كان هذا أكبر مخاوفه
I said, "She'll be happy. She'll ring you up on the mobile."
فقلت: "ستكون سعيدة. ستهاتفك على هاتفك النقال"
She went like a grandmother
ذهبت كجدة
and came back like a tiger.
وعادت كنمر
She walked out of the plane
خرجت من الطائرة
and spoke to the whole press as if she was a veteran.
وتحدثت إلى الصحافة كما لو كانت من المخضرمين
She handled the national press,
تعاملت مع الصحافة المحلية بشكل جيد
and she was a star.
وكانت نجمة
And when I went back six months later, I said, "Where's your husband?"
وحينما عدت بعد ستة أشهر قلت: "أين زوجك؟"
"Oh, somewhere. It doesn't matter."
"آه، في مكان ما. لا يهم"
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Success story.
قصة نجاح
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
I'll just wind up by saying
سأختم فقط بقول
that I think you don't have to look for solutions outside.
بأنني أعتقد أنك لا تحتاج للبحث عن الحلول بالخارج
Look for solutions within.
إبحث عن الحلول بالداخل
And listen to people. They have the solutions in front of you.
واستمع للناس الذين يقدمون الحل أمامك
They're all over the world.
إنهم في جميع أنحاء العالم
Don't even worry.
لا تقلق حتى
Don't listen to the World Bank, listen to the people on the ground.
لا تسمع للبنك الدولي ولكن استمع للناس على الأرض
They have all the solutions in the world.
فإن لديهم جميع الحلول في العالم
I'll end with a quotation by Mahatma Gandhi.
سأنهي حديثي بإقتباس المهاتما غاندي
"First they ignore you,
"في الأول يتجاهلونك
then they laugh at you,
وبعدها يضحكون عليك
then they fight you,
وبعد ذلك يحاربونك
and then you win."
ومن ثم تفوز"
Thank you.
شكراً
(Applause)
(تصفيق)